A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948 FA739E
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739E
93.72 Cubic Feet Document boxes 530-742
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for research with select reports restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739A Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
FA739B Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
FA739C Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
FA739D Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
FA739F Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation’s archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers’ and staff’s archival collections of ‘office files’. When those collections of ‘office files’ were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of “Reports Removed” (or, Reports Transferred”) was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation’s Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation’s own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
Ford Foundation
- Notes on interviews of African mission, 1956 Nov. (Reports 011775) (Box 530)
  Abstract/Summary
  Contents: notes, memoranda, reports, itineraries of the African mission's November 1956 visit to Nigeria. The main purpose of the mission was to study the education system and to develop a program to establish a centralized national system. Includes alpha
  Program Name
  Overseas Division
  Extent
  239 p.
  Education -- Nigeria -- Evaluation; Ford Foundation Program development Nigeria
- Historical financial report: Ford Foundation (Reports 011776), 1955 (Box 530)
  Contains the financial statements, comments and exhibits related to the principal financial transactions of the Ford Foundation for the fiscal years 1936 through 1954.
  Board of Trustees
  1 v.: var pag.: tables,graphs -- 28 cm.
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- History; Ford Foundation
- Attachments from Delegated Authority Project for training workshops, Africa (Reports 011777), 1967
  Ford Foundation general funds supported "Training workshops in fields of major foundation program concern in Africa." - grant description. Archives lacks a complete collection of papers for conferences supported by this grant.
  Related Grant Number
  6400364
  Ford Foundation Series
  Report of the Conference of Permanent and Principal Securities of Local Government held in Lusaka, Zambia, 18-22 Sept., 1967;An evaluation of staff development and human relations workshops conducted by the Ford Foundation in West Africa 1961-1963
  Related Conference
  Guidance Conference(1964 Aug. 17-22:Staff Development Centre, Kaduna, Nigeria);Conference of Permanent and Principal Secretaries of Local Government (1967 Sept. 18-22: Lusaka, Zambia);Guidance Conference (1964 Aug. 17-22: Staff Development Centre, Kadu
  Local officials and employees -- Training of -- Africa, East; Ford Foundation Program development -- Africa, East; Guidance Conference(1964 Aug; Conference of Permanent and Principal Secretaries of Local Gov; Ford Foundation. Near East and Africa; Ford Foundation Program development; Dillard University
- An evaluation of staff development and human relations workshops conducted by the Ford Foundation in West Africa, 1961 (Reports 011777-001), 1965 (Box 530, Reel R-9302)
  Overseas Division/Near East and Africa
  06400364
  Local officials and employees -- Training of -- Africa
- Final report: Guidance conference, August 17-22, 1964, Staff Development Centre, Kaduna, Nigeria (Reports 011777-002) (Box 530, Reel R-9302)
- Report of the conference of permanent and principal secretaries of local government held in Lusaka, Zambia, 18-22 (Reports 011777-003), 1967 (Box 530, Reel R-9302)
- East-West economic relations up to 2000: papers (Reports 011778), 1988 (Box 530)
  Contents: 18 reports by as many authors on economic relations between Eastern and Western bloc nations including the United States and China as well as the European nations.
  United States and International Affairs Program/International Affairs
  07500411;825-0411;835-0793.
  1 archives box (ca. 2.5 in.).
  Workshop on East-West European Economic Interaction (11th: 1988 May 8-14: Berlin and Dresden, GDR)
  East-West trade; International economic relations; Wiener Institut für Internationale Wirtschaftsvergleiche; Akademie der Wissenschaften der DDR. Zentralinstitut für Wirtschaftswissenschaften
- The Arts office: a two-year report, 1978 Nov. (Reports 011779) (Box 530)
  Prepared by Roger Kennedy for the November 1978 meeting of the Arts Committee of the Board of Trustees.
  Board of Trustees;Humanities and the Arts
  ca. 72 leaves.
  Arts -- Endowments -- United States; Ford Foundation. Humanities and the Arts Influence; Ford Foundation. History; Ford Foundation Reorganization; Ford Foundation Humanities and the Arts Program development
- Emerging community development corporation program (Reports 011780), 1983 (Box 531)
  Outlines criteria for selecting emerging CDCs for Ford Foundation support; Foundation funding strategies; partnerships with other funders; and descriptions of emerging CDCs and related technical assistance organizations receiving Ford Foundation grants in
  United States and International Affairs Program/Urban Poverty program
  19 leaves.
  Community development corporations -- United States; Ford Foundation. Urban Poverty
- Memoirs (Reports 011781), 1985 (Box 531)
  Memoirs relate chiefly to McCloy's service in World War II, with the World Bank, and as U.S. High Commissioner for Germany, and to his concern with U.S.-Soviet relations and disarmament. Also includes discussion of his service as Ford Foundation trustee,
  08550040
  249 p., 2 leaves.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from scholarly access.
  World War, 1939-1945; Ford Foundation
- The United States and Germany: the imperative of economic bigemony 1975? (Reports 011782) (Box 531)
  International Division/European and International Affairs
  20 leaves.
  International economic relations
- An independent sector assessment of the Job Training Partnership Act: Final report, program year 1985, 1986 (Reports 011783) (Box 531)
  "This is the third and final report of a two year study analyzing implementation of Title II-A of the Job Training Partnership Act (JTPA) of 1982 ... which provides job training for the economically disadvantaged."-Executive Summary. See also, report #012
  08300488
  viii, 120 p.
  Occupational training -- United States; Employees -- Training of -- United States; Youth -- Employment -- United States; Socially handicapped youth -- Services for -- United States; United States. Job Training Partnership Act JTPA
- Urban poverty in the Andean region: social action and research, 1989 (Reports 011784) (Box 531)
  Developing Countries Program/Argentia and the Southern Cone
  13 leaves.
  Urban poor -- Andes Region -- Evaluation; Action research -- Andes Region; Ford Foundation. Andean Region and Southern Cone; Ford Foundation Program development Andes Region
- Conference papers, Women in the Caribbean Project Conference, Barbados, September 12-16, 1982, 1982 Aug.-Sept. (Reports 011785) (Box 531)
  Contains 16 reports and a list of conference participants.
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  08100881
  17 v. (ca. 2.5 linear in.).
  Women in the Caribbean Project Conference, Barbados, September 12-16, 1982
  Women -- Employment -- Caribbean Area; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women -- Caribbean Area -- Social conditions; Women in agriculture -- Caribbean Area; Women heads of households -- Caribbean Area; Women in development -- Caribbean Area; Women in the Caribbean Project. Conference (1982 Sept. 12-16: Barbados); University of the West Indies (Mona, Jamaica). Institute of Social and Economic Research
- Political considerations within international organisations 1973? (Reports 011786) (Box 531)
  Prepared for the Committee on Atlantic Studies, Atlantic Institute, Brussels meeting, Feb. 26-27, 1973.
  06500161
  25, 3, 8 leaves.
  International agencies -- Europe; International cooperation; Atlantic Institute for International Affairs
- Issues concerning diversity identified at policy research centers (Reports 011787), 1989 (Box 531)
  Prepared for the Ford Foundation's Minority Pipeline Task Force, William Diaz, chair. Based upon visits to twelve policy centers. Discusses the problem of the supply of minority candidates for employment at "think tanks," the institutional culture of thes
  52 leaves.
  Think tank consultancy
  Affirmative action programs -- United States; Research institutes -- United States; Policy scientists -- United States; Minorities -- Employment -- United States; Ford Foundation. Minority Pipeline Task Force
- The Law of the Sea: the United Nations and ocean management: proceedings of the fifth annual conference of the Law of the Sea Institute, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, Rhode Island, June 15-19, 1970 (Reports 011788) (Box 531)
  07000438
  390 p.
  Maritime law -- International cooperation; Sea control -- International cooperation; Environmental monitoring -- International cooperation; Fishery management, International; Ocean bottom -- International cooperation; Law of the Sea Institute. Conference (5th: 1970: Kingston, R.I.)
- The law of the sea: A new Geneva conference: Proceedings of the sixth annual conference of the Law of the Sea Institute, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, Rhode Island, June 21-24, 1971 (Reports 011789) (Box 532)
  231 p.
  Maritime law -- International cooperation; International relations; Sea control -- International cooperation; Law of the Sea Institute. Conference (6th: 1971: Kingston, R.I.)
- Real estate related intermediary sample survey: a look at minority recruitment efforts and prospects for improvement, 1988, Fall (Reports 011790) (Box 532)
  Surveys affirmative action strategies of real-estate related recipients of Ford Foundation Program-Related Investment loans. Archives' copy is missing p. 3.
  United States and International Affairs Program/Program Related Investments
  L88-96 L92-07
  15, 5 leaves.
  Affirmative action programs -- United States; Nonprofit organizations -- United States; Minorities -- Employment -- United States; Real estate business -- United States; Ford Foundation. Program-Related Investments
- Quality of work and quality of care in home care, 1988 Sept. (Reports 011791) (Box 532, Reel R-9302)
  Includes bibliographical references.
  United States and International Affairs Program/Urban Poverty program;United States and International Affairs Program/Program Related Investments
  08500361
  Home care services -- Evaluation; Pickman Consulting Group
- Conservation of historical buildings and areas in Hyderabad city, 1984 Dec. (Reports 011792) (Box 532)
  Volume I contains the 252-leaf comprehensive study report as well as maps, drawings and other supporting documents. Volume II is subtitled "Appendices" and includes meeting minutes, reports and historical background material about the city's architecture
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific;Asia/India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  08050348
  Related Grantee Name
  Hyderabad Urban Development Authority
  2 v. (ca. 700 leaves).
  Urban conservation study
  Historic buildings -- India -- Hyderabad -- Conservation and restoration; City planning and redevelopment law -- India -- Hyderabad; Monuments -- India -- Hyderabad -- Conservation and restoration; Cities and towns -- India -- Growth; Hyderabad Urban Development Authority HUDA; Hyderabad Urban Development Authority
- Report to the Ford Foundation: April 1988 - May 1989, grant # 770-0258F, 1989 (Reports 011793) (Box 532)
  United States and International Affairs Program/Human Rights and Governance
  07700258
  93 leaves.
  African Americans -- Politics and government; Joint Center for Political Studies (U.S.) JCPS Evaluation; Joint Center for Political Studies (U.S.) JCPS Administration; Joint Center for Political Studies (U.S.) JCPS Finance
- Community medicine in Bangladesh: current state and possible future development, 1980 Dec. (Reports 011794) (Box 532)
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific
  08090260
  49 leaves.
  Community health services -- Bangladesh; Public health personnel -- Training of -- Bangladesh
- Sri Lanka trip report, 1990 Feb. (Reports 011795) (Box 533)
  A memorandum to Prof. Gordon Conway discussing Ford Foundation program development in Southeast Asia for the 1990s with regard to human rights, research and training in international affairs, public interest law and legal services, et al.
  Asia/Southeast Asia
  8 leaves.
  Human rights -- Asia, Southeastern; International relations -- Research -- Asia, Southeastern; Public interest law -- Research -- Asia, Southeastern; Ford Foundation Program development Asia, Southeastern
- Attachments 197-?. (Reports 011796), 1970
  Contains papers by the following authors: J. C. Beckett, Lord Chalfont, Brian Crozier, Garrett FitzGerald and F. S. L. Lyons.
  7200018
  5 v. (ca. 117 leaves).
  Northern Ireland;Significant aspects of military security in the conflict area;Communist-led insurrections in the 1970s.;Ireland in the context of the European community;Alternatives open to governments
  Revolutions -- Effect of communism on; Nationalism and communism -- Ireland; Communist strategy; Government, Resistance to -- Great Britain; Government, Resistance to -- Ireland; Terrorism -- Great Britain; Irish Republican Army IRA History; Great Britain; Institute for the Study of Conflict ISC; Irish Republican Army IRA History
- Northern Ireland (Reports 011796-001), 1970 (Box 533)
  07200018
  Revolutions -- Effect of communism on; Nationalism and communism -- Ireland; Communist strategy; Government, Resistance to -- Great Britain; Government, Resistance to -- Ireland; Terrorism -- Great Britain; Irish Republican Army (IRA) -- History
- Significant aspects of military security in the conflict area (Reports 011796-002), undated (Box 533)
- Communist-led insurrections in the 1970s (Reports 011796-003), 1971 (Box 533)
- Ireland in the context of the European community (Reports 011796-004), undated (Box 533)
- The alternatives open to governments (Reports 011796-005), undated (Box 533)
- Final report of the national Interest on Lawyers Trust Accounts (IOLTA) Clearinghouse 1983-1986 (Reports 011797) (Box 533)
  Includes reproductions of articles, newsletters, minutes of IOLTA meetings, litigation challenging IOLTA and court orders and legislation establishing IOLTA programs.
  08500225
  861 p.
  American Bar Association Commission on Interest on Lawyers' Trust Accounts
  Legal aid -- United States; Bar associations -- United States; Charity laws and legislation -- United States; Florida Justice Institute
- Helping families grow strong: new directions in public policy: papers from the Colloquium on Public Policy and Family Support, 1990 Apr. (Reports 011798) (Box 533)
  Urban Poverty program
  08400282
  246 p.
  Colloquium on Public Policy and Family Support (1989 April: Annapolis, Md.).
  Family services -- United States -- Congresses; Education and state -- United States -- Congresses; Center for the Study of Social Policy (Washington, D.C.)
- Preparing urban teachers for the technological future: a report to the Ford Foundation (Reports 011799), 1985 (Box 533)
  [78] leaves.
  Education, Urban -- United States; Teachers -- Training of -- United States; Education -- Computer-assisted instruction -- United States; Bank Street College of Education. Center for Children and Technology
- First year evaluation of Local Initiatives Support Corporation, 1984 Sept. (Reports 011800) (Box 533)
  v. (various pagings).
  Community development, Urban -- United States; Action research -- United States; Local Initiatives Support Corporation
- Report to the Ford Foundation: grant #760-0397, 1977 Dec. (Reports 011801) (Box 534)
  Also includes: Annual report of the president 1976-1977 and a commemorative of George Washington Carver's induction into the Hall of Fame for Great Americans, 1977.
  Education and Research/Higher Education & Research
  07600397
  Education, Higher -- Endowments -- United States; Ford Foundation. Higher Education and Research
- Self-help projects for refugees in the Red Sea province of the Sudan, 1980 (Reports 011802) (Box 534)
  International Division/Middle East and Africa
  08190188
  29 [i.e. 30] leaves.
  Refugees -- Eritrea; Social service and race relations -- Red Sea Hills (Egypt and Sudan)
- Eritrean refugees in the Sudan (Reports 011803), 1980 (Box 534)
  28 leaves.
  Refugees -- Eritrea
- Immigration bail administration: a case study of the role of the immigration court, 1985 Dec. (Reports 011804) (Box 534)
  08550182
  Emigration and immigration law -- United States; Bail -- United States; Court congestion and delay -- United States
- The Child Survival/Fair Start initiative: a mid-term progress report prepared for the Ford Foundation, 1986 (Reports 011805) (Box 534)
  33 leaves.
  Infant health services -- Finance -- United States; Maternal health services -- Finance -- United States; Child health services -- Finance -- United States; Community health services -- Finance -- United States; Maternal and infant welfare -- United States; Ford Foundation. Child Survival/Fair Start for Children CS/FS
- An action-research project on universal primary education: the plan and the process ca. (Reports 011806), 1982 (Box 534)
  Shows statistics and scope of project undertaken by the Indian Institute of Education, Pune, India.
  Developing Countries Program/India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  37 leaves.
  Education, Primary -- India -- Aims and objectives; Education -- Experimental methods -- India; Action research -- India; Indian Institute of Education; Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi
- Appraising and improving canal irrigation, 1981 Apr. (Reports 011807) (Box 534)
  A look at India's gravity canal systems from a multidisciplinary standpoint. Reworks hypotheses of Robert Steckler.
  [30] leaves.
  Irrigation canals and flumes -- India; Irrigation efficiency -- India; Agriculture -- India; Farm management -- India; Action research -- India; Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi
- The new era of irrigation management in India, 1981 Jan. (Reports 011808) (Box 534)
  The paper explores the process of effectively accelerating irrigation management in India.
  47 leaves.
  Irrigation -- Management -- India; Agricultural innovations -- India; Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi
- Restoration of the Himalayas (Reports 011809), 1980 (Box 534)
  Discussion of the implementation of a program to help restore and maintain "the unique geographic and social structure" of the Himalayas. Includes inter-office correspondence. re: this paper.
  [17] leaves.
  Korwa (Indic people); Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi
- Culture strategy paper, October 5 (Reports 011810), 1982 (Box 534)
  Strategy paper written for Foundation's reorganization and restructuring of program development in 1980-1981.
  39 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Culture diffusion -- India; Arts and society -- India; Cultural property--Protection -- Finance -- India; Cultural property--Protection -- Asia, Southeastern; Arts -- Finance -- India; Ford Foundation. Developing Country Programs; Ford Foundation Education and Culture
- Community Development Block Grant Program: Attachments, 1978-1986. (Reports 011811) (Box 534)
  Attachments include publications such as Citizen's Action Guides to help community groups "monitor local and federal public programs and take part in government policy and budget decisions", as well as Community Development Guides, Urban Development Actio
  United States and International Affairs Program/Urban Poverty program; National Affairs program/UMD; National Affairs program/Social Development
  06900120
  12 v. (3 linear in.).
  Citizen's action guide
  Community development -- Citizen participation -- United States; Community education -- United States; Action research -- United States; Municipal budgets -- Law and legislation -- Citizen participation; United States; Community Development Block Grant Program (U.S.)
- Minorities in academic careers: the experience of Ford Foundation Fellows (Reports 011812), 1984 (Box 535)
  Report (114 l.) was based on and includes an appendix (67 l.) and a supplemental appendix (120 l.) which list black, Mexican American, Puerto Rican and Native American recipients of the doctoral fellowships sponsored by the Ford Foundation between 1969 an
  United States and International Affairs Program/Education and Culture
  08200946
  The Regents of the University of Michigan, Dearborn
  [301] leaves -- 28 cm.
  Minorities -- Education (Graduate) -- United States; Minorities -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Ford Foundation. Education and Culture; Ford Foundation Fellows
- The tenant management demonstration program: a documentation of the first eighteen months of program implementation (Reports 011813), 1978 (Box 535)
  Includes 7 case studies of tenant management programs in public housing developments around the United States.
  National Affairs/Urban and Metropolitan Development
  07600045
  [177] leaves.
  Public housing -- United States -- Management; Public housing -- Resident satisfaction; National Tenant Management Demonstration
- My comments and recommendations for FF health and nutrition programming, October 16 (Reports 011814), 1980 (Box 535)
  Includes list of Health and Nutrition Grants received by New Delhi office 1971-1980 and plans for funding and projects for 1981-1983.
  International Division/Population Program
  [11] leaves -- 28 cm.
  My comments and recommendations for Ford Foundation health and nutrition programming
  Population assistance -- India; Health promotion -- India; Nutrition -- India -- Evaluation; Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi
- A comparative study of attempts to formulate social policy at the national level in the U.S.A., United Kingdom and Israel: a study of processes of national social policy making (Reports 011815), 1980 (Box 535)
  Includes list of interviews and official documents in addition to bibliographical references.